<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Food | All your writing are belong to us]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.cosminn.net/blog/categories/food/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.cosminn.net/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-05T10:18:34-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.cosminn.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Cosmin Nicolaescu]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Year of New Restaurants]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.cosminn.net/blog/2014/10/04/a-year-of-new-restaurants/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-04T22:07:18-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.cosminn.net/blog/2014/10/04/a-year-of-new-restaurants</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Seattle is a city full of terrific restaurants with amazing food. And after living
there for four years, I&rsquo;m pretty happy that I probably ate at ~80% of them. But
that means that there&rsquo;s still probably over a dozen places that are really tasty
which I didn&rsquo;t try out. Even in my last few weeks living there, I was finding
little gems, in the form of lunch trucks around the city or small places in
Pike&rsquo;s Place. Given that SF has at least an order of magnitude more restaurants,
and the average quality is higher due to the inherent competition, a new
strategy was needed.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>The paradox</h3>

<p>The reality is that, in cities like San Francisco or Seattle, most restaurants
serve good food. A high number of them have exceptional food. And a few
special have something you can&rsquo;t find anywhere else (like <a href="http://www.paseoseattle.com/">Paseo</a> and
<a href="http://www.salumicuredmeats.com/">Salumi</a>). And this is where the paradox comes in: once you have a set of
good restaurants, you&rsquo;re guaranteed to have a tasty meal. But by going to the
same places, you&rsquo;re missing out on discovering another delicious
restaurant, at the risk of being slightly disappointed occasionally.</p>

<h3>The plot</h3>

<p>Since I suffer from the &ldquo;once you find something good, stick to it&rdquo; syndrome, I
needed to create something which breaks the usual pattern. So, over the course
of the summer I&rsquo;ve been planning a little adventure for San Francisco:
<strong>over the course of a year, I will not go to the same restaurant twice</strong>. This
will act as a forcing function to try out a new place of similar (or
completely new) cuisine.</p>

<h3>The exceptions</h3>

<p>Like anything with rules, there are exceptions. The list below exists not to
allow me to game the game I set up for myself, but to set expectations for
scenarios I <em>know</em> could result in a check-in to the same place.</p>

<ul>
<li>Work lunch places &mdash; there&rsquo;s only a few around one&rsquo;s work
place, and when I go it&rsquo;s typically in a group.</li>
<li>Takeout/Delivery places &mdash; similarly, there&rsquo;s only a few around one&rsquo;s home,
and it&rsquo;s convenient to be able to get some dinner late at night.</li>
<li>Brunch vs. Dinner &mdash; the same restaurant can be repeated if one of the meals
is a brunch and another is dinner. The menus are typically entirely
different, so it&rsquo;s really like trying out two different restaurants.</li>
<li>Out of town visitors &mdash; hopefully friends from Seattle or other parts of the
world will come to SF. When they do, I want to be able to take them to the
best places.</li>
<li>Group events &mdash; if someone wants to have their birthday at a restaurant I
already ate at, it would be pretty awkward to try to convince them to go
somewhere else because of my silly rules; and it would be a shame to not be
able to join them.</li>
</ul>


<h3>The details</h3>

<p>So, between October 1st, 2014 &ndash; October 1st, 2015:</p>

<ul>
<li>you should not see two check-ins at the same restaurant.</li>
<li>when checking in, each restaurant will get one of the following ratings:
<em>Sucks I can&rsquo;t try it out for another year</em>; <em>Meh, probably not coming back
for a year anyways</em> or <em>It&rsquo;s going to be much longer than a year
until I come back here</em>.</li>
<li>Exceptional places may end up with a blog entry along with some pictures (and
if you&rsquo;re curious about some place, just ping for more details).</li>
</ul>


<p>There&rsquo;s quite a few people I mentioned this to, who don&rsquo;t think I can pull it
through. And given my habits in Seattle, I do agree it&rsquo;s going to require lots of
discipline. At the very least, it should make for some fun stories and hopefully
great food.</p>

<p>(obligatory <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/firstworldproblems">#firstworldproblems</a> reference)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
